<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Standards on MDL Community website</title>
    <link>http://www.mdl.community/tags/standards/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Standards on MDL Community website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mike K Smith</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.mdl.community/tags/standards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Production &amp; Development Language Standards</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/08/standards_production_development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/08/standards_production_development/</guid>
      <description>A subgroup of the DDMoRe Language Standards Community is discussing how to support production and development of the DDMoRe Language Standards
During the IMI DDMoRe project, we developed the DDMoRe Language Standards (MDL, PharmML, SO) and integrated these with the associated tools libpharmml, libso, etc. to form the basis of the DDMoRe Interoperability Framework enabling modelling and simulation workflow based on the MDL representation of a model and automated conversion through PharmML to target software and conversion of the output back to the Standard Output object and from there back to R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#39;...but I only use NONMEM&#39;</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/23/but_i_only_use_nonmem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/23/but_i_only_use_nonmem/</guid>
      <description>Do you want others to use your models?Well, you SAY you only use NONMEM (although I don’t believe that - see below) but ultimately I’m sure that you’d like other people to use your model and/or the inferences based on it.
The use of modelling and simulation has expanded into quantitative pharmacology, pharmacology (Pop PK and PKPD), disease modelling, model-based meta-analysis (MBMA), cost-effectiveness and many more. Many different quantitative disciplines are now involved in building models, evaluating models, using models and modelling outputs to interpret data, plan studies or make decisions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About MDL and this website</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/22/about_mdl_and_this_website/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 10:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/22/about_mdl_and_this_website/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the DDMoRe Model Description Language (MDL) Community page.This website will provide a resource for anyone wishing to encode models with MDL, will help you understand MDL structure and features and provides a place for you to log bugs, issues, feature requests and suggestions.
What is MDL?MDL is a human writeable and human readable language designed to describe pharmacometric models. It is intended to be largely agnostic about the choice of target tool.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>