<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community on MDL Community website</title>
    <link>http://www.mdl.community/tags/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community on MDL Community website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mike K Smith</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 09:04:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.mdl.community/tags/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>MDL-Editor version 1.7.1</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2018/06/27/mdleditor_update_1.7.1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 09:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2018/06/27/mdleditor_update_1.7.1/</guid>
      <description>A new release of the MDL Editor is available at the following link: http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/current/
This version fixes some issues with PharmML conversion as well as updates to libraries used in the editor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community at PAGE 2017 - Minutes</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/08/09/language_community_minutes_page2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/08/09/language_community_minutes_page2017/</guid>
      <description>At PAGE the language community group had a meeting on 8th June 2017.
Present were Rikard Nordgren, Maciej Swat, Stuart Moodie, Gunnar Yngman and (over the phone) Mike K Smith.
PharmMLProduction and development tracks for PharmMLStuart presented the suggestion of having two tracks of PharmML versions. One “production” (“stable”) track and one “development” track. The production PharmML is intended to be the one supported by tools and libraries and the development version will when ready be (whole or in parts) merged into the development track.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community at PAGE 2017</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/22/language_community_page2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2017 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/22/language_community_page2017/</guid>
      <description>DDMoRe Language Community at PAGE 2017, Budapest, Hungary
There are plans for the DDMoRe Language Community to meet at the PAGE 2017 conference held in Budapest, Hungary from 6-9 June.
Current plans are to meet up with Rikard Nordgren at the PsN stand in the exhibit area at 13:45pm on Thursday 8th.
Also, look out for the poster I-14 “Execution of complex Bayesian workflows with the DDMoRe Interoperability Framework: a case study in the diabetes area” by Christiana Larizza, Elisa Borella, Lorenzo Pasotti, Palma Tartaglione, Mike K Smith, Stuart Moodie and Paolo Magni.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community - Meeting minutes 29th March 2017</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/31/language_community_minutes_20170329/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/31/language_community_minutes_20170329/</guid>
      <description>The DDMoRe Language Community meeting was held 29th of March 2017
SummaryWe should contribute Agenda items for the meeting, report bugs, issues and features requests for MDL and the website through Github.Mike K Smith gave a brief walkthrough of MDL structure and we looked at a Pop PK model for Factor IX developed by Aki Suzuki (Pfizer) as an example.We discussed a Pop PK / PKPD library of “stock” models that would be documented and encoded in MDL, NMTRAN, and open source tools such as nlmixr, mrgsolve, saemix, PopED, PFIM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community - Meeting minutes 22nd Feb 2017</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/08/language_community_minutes_20170222/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/08/language_community_minutes_20170222/</guid>
      <description>On 22nd of February 2017 we had the inaugural meeting of the DDMoRe Language Community.
SummaryWe recapped the scope of the DDMoRe Language Community and how it fits with the DDMoRe Foundation, the current status of each of the DDMoRe Language Standards, how they are used and what associated tools are available.We recognise that we need to distinguish between production and development versions of the languages.There is scope for satellite meetings at PAGE and ACOP to allow community members get together to share ideas, encode models using the standards, develop tools (hackathon) etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/19/ddmore_language_community/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 13:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/19/ddmore_language_community/</guid>
      <description>On 17th January 2017 we announced the start of the DDMoRe Language Community.
What is the DDMoRe Language Community for?The DDMoRe model exchange standards - the Model Description Language (MDL), Pharmacometrics Markup Language (PharmML), and Standard Output object (SO) - are open-source standards. The IMI DDMoRe project delivered a proof of concept implementation of an Interoperability Framework which incorporates these standards and shows how, having encoded the model using MDL, the modeller can then perform a complete pharmacometrics workflow (estimation, diagnostics, prediction / simulation and optimal design) without having to recode the model for different target software tools.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>