<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MDL Community website</title>
    <link>http://www.mdl.community/</link>
    <description>Recent content on MDL Community website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mike K Smith</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 09:04:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.mdl.community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>MDL-Editor version 1.7.0</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2018/06/21/mdleditor_update_1.7.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 09:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2018/06/21/mdleditor_update_1.7.0/</guid>
      <description>A new release of the MDL Editor is available at the following link: http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.7.0/
This version fixes some issues with PharmML conversion as well as updates to libraries used in the editor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community at PAGE 2017 - Minutes</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/08/09/language_community_minutes_page2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/08/09/language_community_minutes_page2017/</guid>
      <description>At PAGE the language community group had a meeting on 8th June 2017.
Present were Rikard Nordgren, Maciej Swat, Stuart Moodie, Gunnar Yngman and (over the phone) Mike K Smith.
PharmMLProduction and development tracks for PharmMLStuart presented the suggestion of having two tracks of PharmML versions. One “production” (“stable”) track and one “development” track. The production PharmML is intended to be the one supported by tools and libraries and the development version will when ready be (whole or in parts) merged into the development track.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community at PAGE 2017</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/22/language_community_page2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2017 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/22/language_community_page2017/</guid>
      <description>DDMoRe Language Community at PAGE 2017, Budapest, Hungary
There are plans for the DDMoRe Language Community to meet at the PAGE 2017 conference held in Budapest, Hungary from 6-9 June.
Current plans are to meet up with Rikard Nordgren at the PsN stand in the exhibit area at 13:45pm on Thursday 8th.
Also, look out for the poster I-14 “Execution of complex Bayesian workflows with the DDMoRe Interoperability Framework: a case study in the diabetes area” by Christiana Larizza, Elisa Borella, Lorenzo Pasotti, Palma Tartaglione, Mike K Smith, Stuart Moodie and Paolo Magni.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Production &amp; Development Language Standards</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/08/standards_production_development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/05/08/standards_production_development/</guid>
      <description>A subgroup of the DDMoRe Language Standards Community is discussing how to support production and development of the DDMoRe Language Standards
During the IMI DDMoRe project, we developed the DDMoRe Language Standards (MDL, PharmML, SO) and integrated these with the associated tools libpharmml, libso, etc. to form the basis of the DDMoRe Interoperability Framework enabling modelling and simulation workflow based on the MDL representation of a model and automated conversion through PharmML to target software and conversion of the output back to the Standard Output object and from there back to R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community - Meeting minutes 29th March 2017</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/31/language_community_minutes_20170329/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/31/language_community_minutes_20170329/</guid>
      <description>The DDMoRe Language Community meeting was held 29th of March 2017
SummaryWe should contribute Agenda items for the meeting, report bugs, issues and features requests for MDL and the website through Github.Mike K Smith gave a brief walkthrough of MDL structure and we looked at a Pop PK model for Factor IX developed by Aki Suzuki (Pfizer) as an example.We discussed a Pop PK / PKPD library of “stock” models that would be documented and encoded in MDL, NMTRAN, and open source tools such as nlmixr, mrgsolve, saemix, PopED, PFIM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community - Meeting minutes 22nd Feb 2017</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/08/language_community_minutes_20170222/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/03/08/language_community_minutes_20170222/</guid>
      <description>On 22nd of February 2017 we had the inaugural meeting of the DDMoRe Language Community.
SummaryWe recapped the scope of the DDMoRe Language Community and how it fits with the DDMoRe Foundation, the current status of each of the DDMoRe Language Standards, how they are used and what associated tools are available.We recognise that we need to distinguish between production and development versions of the languages.There is scope for satellite meetings at PAGE and ACOP to allow community members get together to share ideas, encode models using the standards, develop tools (hackathon) etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#39;...but I only use NONMEM&#39;</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/23/but_i_only_use_nonmem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/23/but_i_only_use_nonmem/</guid>
      <description>Do you want others to use your models?Well, you SAY you only use NONMEM (although I don’t believe that - see below) but ultimately I’m sure that you’d like other people to use your model and/or the inferences based on it.
The use of modelling and simulation has expanded into quantitative pharmacology, pharmacology (Pop PK and PKPD), disease modelling, model-based meta-analysis (MBMA), cost-effectiveness and many more. Many different quantitative disciplines are now involved in building models, evaluating models, using models and modelling outputs to interpret data, plan studies or make decisions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/19/ddmore_language_community/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 13:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/19/ddmore_language_community/</guid>
      <description>On 17th January 2017 we announced the start of the DDMoRe Language Community.
What is the DDMoRe Language Community for?The DDMoRe model exchange standards - the Model Description Language (MDL), Pharmacometrics Markup Language (PharmML), and Standard Output object (SO) - are open-source standards. The IMI DDMoRe project delivered a proof of concept implementation of an Interoperability Framework which incorporates these standards and shows how, having encoded the model using MDL, the modeller can then perform a complete pharmacometrics workflow (estimation, diagnostics, prediction / simulation and optimal design) without having to recode the model for different target software tools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MDL User Guide and Reference Manual now available</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/06/mdluserguide_announcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 09:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/06/mdluserguide_announcement/</guid>
      <description>The MDL User Guide and Reference Manual are now available online: https://modeldefinitionlanguage.github.io/MDLUserGuide/.
There is a toolbar at the top of the manual that allows you to see the section browser, search within the manual, change text attributes while reading, edit a page (via Github) and download the manual as PDF or ePub (coming soon!).
The User Guide will be maintained and updated on Github at https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/MDLUserGuide. We encourage the community to contribute to and update the manual either by editing .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/page/faq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/page/faq/</guid>
      <description>Why MDL? Why design a whole new language (MDL) to describe models? The MDL has been designed to allow users to specify models in a consistent language, regardless of the target tool they prefer to use for a given task (e.g. estimation), and regardless of whether they intend to use the model for estimation, simulation, or optimal design. This eliminates the transcoding needed today when using a model in a different tool or for a different purpose.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MDL Editor now available</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/24/mdleditor_announcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 16:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/24/mdleditor_announcement/</guid>
      <description>The MDL-Editor is now available for download. This is a cross-platform, Eclipse-based Integrated Development Environment (IDE) for writing MDL models incorporating syntax highlighting and grammar checks. It is available for Windows ( 32bit and 64bit), Linux and Mac OS. Simply download the zip file and unzip to an appropriate location. An update site has been configured within Eclipse so that future updates to the MDL-Editor can be retrieved from within Eclipse without having to download another zip file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About MDL</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 10:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/page/about/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the DDMoRe Model Description Language (MDL) Community page. This website will provide a resource for anyone wishing to encode models with MDL, will help you understand MDL structure and features and provides a place for you to log bugs, issues, feature requests and suggestions.
What is MDL? MDL is a human writeable and human readable language designed to describe pharmacometric models. It is intended to be largely agnostic about the choice of target tool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About MDL and this website</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/22/about_mdl_and_this_website/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 10:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/22/about_mdl_and_this_website/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the DDMoRe Model Description Language (MDL) Community page.This website will provide a resource for anyone wishing to encode models with MDL, will help you understand MDL structure and features and provides a place for you to log bugs, issues, feature requests and suggestions.
What is MDL?MDL is a human writeable and human readable language designed to describe pharmacometric models. It is intended to be largely agnostic about the choice of target tool.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>