<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MDL Community website</title>
    <link>http://www.mdl.community/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on MDL Community website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mike K Smith</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 14:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.mdl.community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>&#39;...but I only use NONMEM&#39;</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/20/but_i_only_use_nonmem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/20/but_i_only_use_nonmem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE

/BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;do-you-want-others-to-use-your-models&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do you want others to use your models?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;SAY&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; you only use NONMEM (although I don’t believe that - see below) but ultimately I’m sure that you’d like other people to use your model and/or the inferences based on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of modelling and simulation has expanded into quantitative pharmacology, pharmacology (Pop PK and PKPD), disease modelling, model-based meta-analysis (MBMA), cost-effectiveness and many more. Many different quantitative disciplines are now involved in building models, evaluating models, using models and modelling outputs to interpret data, plan studies or make decisions. For a given model to be useful (and used!) across all of these groups we need to find a way that we can express the model such that anybody else that wants to use it can do so for their own purposes, whatever those are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-do-you-share-models&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How do you share models?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;i-share-via-nmtran-other-code&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I share via (NMTRAN / other) code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://discuss.go-isop.org/t/isop-global-survey-how-do-you-share/657&#34;&gt;A recent survey by the International Society of Pharmacometrics&lt;/a&gt; found that ~75% of respondents primarily use NONMEM as their main tool for analysis. This would support the strategy for sharing NMTRAN models &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; the pharmacometrics community, but what about outside of it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the statistics community there is a growing use of R as a tool for analytical work, sometimes calling other tools e.g. C++, Java, etc. but still, within industry, SAS is primarily used as the clinical trial reporting tool of choice. So if you’re interested in getting statisticians to use your model, then what language should you choose for sharing? Do you expect them to learn and understand the NMTRAN code? Do you both try to translate to R? What about SAS? Will you learn R or SAS sufficient to be able to share your model?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;i-share-via-publications&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I share via publications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing down the maths of a model is a great way to share the model between quantitative disciplines. It’s a universal language and brings with it rigour and a lack of ambiguity. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BUT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; while two modellers can agree on the maths of a problem, the implementation may vary between two software tools such that it may be easy to implement in one tool, but very difficult (impossible?) in another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-problem-of-reproducibility&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The problem of reproducibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reproducibility means many things to many different people. For now, let’s focus on being able to re-run an estimation step for a given set of data and the ability to confirm that the parameter estimates match those presented by the original analyst. Even in this minimalist definition of reproducibility we can face problems reproducing the original analyst’s work if we don’t get &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the code they ran, match the same software and environment settings, etc. The problem gets worse if we’re trying to convert from one software tool to another along the way or if we’re trying to implement the mathematical and statistical models presented in a publication if we don’t have access to the original code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;nonmem-doesnt-do-everything&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NONMEM doesn’t do &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;EVERYTHING&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NONMEM and associated tools e.g. PsN have some limitations in available functionality, for example optimal trial design. And while NONMEM &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; be used for prediction and simulation of new designs, regimens and scenarios there are a growing number of freely available, open-source tools that can also do this and arguably more easily &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;given that the model is encoded in the appropriate input format for that tool&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, either we have to write a load of NMTRAN to &lt;tool X&gt; translators (some exist e.g. Pirana) or we have to use or develop a master language that can easily translate to NMTRAN, but also to other tools e.g. Certara / Pharsight’s PML or DDMoRe’s MDL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;open-source-tools-are-growing-in-use&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Open-source tools are growing in use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a rising number of free, open-source software for nonlinear mixed effects modelling and simulation (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.saemix.biostat.fr/&#34;&gt;saemix&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nlmixrdevelopment/nlmixr&#34;&gt;nlmixr&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://simulx.webpopix.org/&#34;&gt;mlxR / simulx&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://metrumrg.com/opensourcetools.html&#34;&gt;mrgsolve&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hallowkm/RxODE&#34;&gt;RxODE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ronkeizer/PKPDsim&#34;&gt;PKPDsim&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfim.biostat.fr/&#34;&gt;PFIM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://poped.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;PopED&lt;/a&gt; ) and while use of these tools may be limited today, they provide a means for performing the majority of modelling and simulation tasks with no cost to the analyst. More integration of these tools into pharmacometrics toolset and workflow would benefit many, especially those who cannot get access to NONMEM licenses, yet still may wish to use disease and therapeutic drug models in their work or for predicting outcomes for patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 10 years ago, it would have been hard to imagine the case that S-Plus would be thoroughly supplanted by R, to the point where it ceased to be a supported product by the company (Tibco) that bought it from Insightful. And yet, here we are. &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/popularity/&#34;&gt;R is rising in popularity as an analytical engine (often coupled with other technologies)&lt;/a&gt;. So to dismiss open-source solutions as “irrelevant” may be regarded as a short-sighted view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;open-source-standards-can-shape-the-discipline&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;(Open-source) Standards can shape the discipline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advent and growth of [SBML] (&lt;a href=&#34;http://authors.library.caltech.edu/2099/1/HUCieesb04.pdf&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://authors.library.caltech.edu/2099/1/HUCieesb04.pdf&lt;/a&gt;) has had a profound effect on the systems biology modelling world - impacting model sharing and tool development.With SBML as a basis for import and export of models to and from software tools, the community now has a means to quickly and easily share models, regardless of the preferred tools for individuals, laboratories or companies. This sparked development of many open-source tools, but also forced integration of SBML into existing and novel commercial tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a moment, just compare the growth our community in pharmacometrics made in comparison to other fields such as computational biology, genetics, ecology to name a few. The experts in these fields are scientists, similar to us, and not software engineers. Yet, they made massive strides in science mainly due to their adoption of open source methods and tools. Experts working in the industry put their developed tools and materials out in the open, a culture that pharmacometrics experts in the industry have yet to embrace after all these years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental requirement is a change in culture and thinking in our community. To facilitate getting over the initial hurdles of this culture change, tools that allow this transition are required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DDMoRe model exchange standards could be revolutionary for model sharing and interoperability within the pharmacometrics discipline but also beyond into other quantitative disciplines e.g. statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;unified-workflow-agnostic-to-software-tool-choice-is-a-good-aim&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unified workflow agnostic to software tool choice is a good aim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, any time the modeller (or anyone using a given model) needs to transcode the model from one software tool to another, we should ensure that the transcoded model is equivalent to the original &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; making any new inferences from it. This adds an overhead of time and resource into the modelling and simulation process and brings with it the possibility of errors introduced while translating from one implementation to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideal workflow would be agnostic to the tool used for a given task. It would be ideal to be able to substitute one tool for another in the workflow and carry on with subsequent down-stream activities, with no intervention from the user to activities outside of the workflow. This would greatly improve reproducibility and portability of workflow from one analyst to another and also across quantitative disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MDL, along with the DDMoRe model exchange standards, &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B6l15jR-cIWdMTlKUlY4LTJ2ajA/view?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;has achieved this aim using the Interoperability Framework&lt;/a&gt;. In this example we show end-to-end workflow using a variety of tools to perform exploratory analysis, estimation, model diagnostics &amp;amp; qualification, prediction, simulation and optimal design all without having to recode the model in any way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-future-with-mdl-and-the-ddmore-model-exchange-standards&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The future with MDL and the DDMoRe model exchange standards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has never been a better time to get engaged with the DDMoRe model exchange standards through the DDMoRe Language Community. We have shown that the concepts of interoperability are achievable, we have &amp;gt;100 models on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://repository.ddmore.eu/&#34;&gt;DDMoRe Model Repository&lt;/a&gt; and we have made these languages open-source so that the community can capitalise on work already done and contribute to the future state of these standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgement&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgement:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vjd&#34;&gt;Vijay Ivaturi&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kylebmetrum&#34;&gt;kylebmetrum&lt;/a&gt; for comments and additions to this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD




/BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DDMoRe Language Community</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/19/ddmore_language_community/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 13:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/19/ddmore_language_community/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE

/BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On 17th January 2017 we announced the start of the DDMoRe Language Community.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-the-ddmore-language-community-for&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is the DDMoRe Language Community for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DDMoRe model exchange standards - the Model Description Language (MDL), Pharmacometrics Markup Language (PharmML), and Standard Output object (SO) - are open-source standards. The IMI DDMoRe project delivered a proof of concept implementation of an Interoperability Framework which incorporates these standards and shows how, having encoded the model using MDL, the modeller can then perform a complete pharmacometrics workflow (estimation, diagnostics, prediction / simulation and optimal design) without having to recode the model for different target software tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DDMoRe Language Community is intended as a forum for discussion of the standards, how they can evolve, feature requests, bug reporting, finding help etc. It will also work as a hub to share how the standards are being used in integrating tools into a unified workflow through conversion from and to PharmML, use of the Standard Output object and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DDMoRe Foundation will continue to have the overview and strategic vision for the integration of the standards into existing products: the Interoperability Framework, DDMoRe Model Repository. But the community can assist the Foundation in specifying, reviewing, refining new language features or assisting with existing or new converter tools for the different target software that we might want to use within the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-can-i-contribute-to-the-ddmore-language-community&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How can I contribute to the DDMoRe Language Community?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways that you can contribute, with a variety of levels of engagement and commitment. We encourage &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to contribute, with big &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; small contributions. The ultimate success of these standards depends on building a community where everyone is engaged and contributing to the community, sharing what you’re doing with the standards or helping to refine them to meet your needs. We want &lt;strong&gt;YOU&lt;/strong&gt; - we &lt;strong&gt;NEED YOU&lt;/strong&gt; - to be part of building this exciting new community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;language-development&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Language development&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DDMoRe Language standards are integrated through the language converters employed within the DDMoRe Interoperability Framework. Going forward, the DDMoRe Foundation will aim to incrementally release the languages into “production”, so that the languages are well aligned and that converters, technology and the DDMoRe repository are set up to use this latest version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that doesn’t stop the community from working on the language standards in parallel - having “development” versions, discussing, refining, incorporating suggestions and fixes where necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MDL language standards and associated tools are hosted on Github at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage&lt;/a&gt;. We encourage the community members to join Github, fork the repositories, make changes and then submit a “pull request” for discussion of the changes. There is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://guides.github.com/activities/hello-world/&#34;&gt;good primer available on Github process&lt;/a&gt; if you’re not familiar with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to contribute to documentation of the language standards (particularly MDL) then the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/MDLUserGuide&#34;&gt;MDL User Guide is now on Github&lt;/a&gt;. The guide uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/bookdown&#34;&gt;RStudio’s “bookdown”&lt;/a&gt; format - you edit R markdown pages which are then rendered into the online book and PDF version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to contribute to the MDL Community website, to contribute blog posts “How to…” or “Getting started…” guides, then please pull the “draft” branch of the website repository, add .Rmd files to the /content/post/ and create a pull request for review. Alternatively, send an R markdown file containing your post to Mike K Smith (Mike.K.Smith at Pfizer.com).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to raise a bug report, ask a question, make a feature request then you can raise a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/website/issues&#34;&gt;Github Issue on the website repository&lt;/a&gt;. We will then reassign this to the appropriate repository and the resolution can be discussed and tracked via Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;tool-development&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tool development&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish to develop new tools or contribute to development of existing tools using the DDMoRe language standards, then we can point you in the direction of the appropriate technology and associated subject matter experts to help you get started. If you don’t need that assistance, please go right ahead and develop away! All we ask is that you respect the license agreements from the existing software (most of which uses AGPL, ASL or variants of open-source licenses) and we ask that you also keep the community informed what you’re doing, so that others don’t reinvent the wheel and/or could help contribute to your development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any work done on the existing standards and associated toolsets will be open-source and we would encourage new development to be similarly open-sourced so that the community can benefit from and bootstrap off this work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-will-my-contribution-be-recognised&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How will my contribution be recognised?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you contribute to the language standards, tools, website, User Guide through Github, then we’d like to have your Github profile linked via the MDL Community website. That way, others will know what you’ve contributed, and can also link through to any other work you might be involved in through Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome and will recognise &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;contribution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;active engagement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to the MDL community. The DDMoRe Foundation is working on how to recognise individual contribution to the Foundation, and this will be announced at some point in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, please do let us know what you think, how you’d like to get engaged, what kinds of things you might want to do with the standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The future is out there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgement&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgement:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Chris Shilling (Chris.Shilling at florinpartnership.com) for his comments and additions to this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD




/BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MDL User Guide and Reference Manual now available</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/06/mdluserguide_announcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 09:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2017/01/06/mdluserguide_announcement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE

/BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MDL User Guide and Reference Manual are now available online: &lt;a href=&#34;https://modeldefinitionlanguage.github.io/MDLUserGuide/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://modeldefinitionlanguage.github.io/MDLUserGuide/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a toolbar at the top of the manual that allows you to see the section browser, search within the manual, change text attributes while reading, edit a page (via Github) and download the manual as PDF or ePub (coming soon!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The User Guide will be maintained and updated on Github at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/MDLUserGuide&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/MDLUserGuide&lt;/a&gt;. We encourage the community to contribute to and update the manual either by editing .Rmd files directly on Github or by making a copy of the repository, making changes and submitting a pull request, according to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://guides.github.com/introduction/flow/&#34;&gt;Github workflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The User Guide is compiled using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rstudio/bookdown&#34;&gt;RStudio’s bookdown package&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.name/&#34;&gt;Yihui Xie&lt;/a&gt; has provided &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/bookdown/&#34;&gt;a comprehensive guide to bookdown&lt;/a&gt;. By downloading bookdown and dependent packages, it is possible for anybody to recompile the manual using R.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD




/BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/page/faq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/page/faq/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-mdl&#34;&gt;Why MDL?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-design-a-whole-new-language-mdl-to-describe-models&#34;&gt;Why design a whole new language (MDL) to describe models?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MDL has been designed to allow users to specify models in a consistent language,
regardless of the target tool they prefer to use for a given task (e.g. estimation),
and regardless of whether they intend to use the model for estimation, simulation,
or optimal design. This eliminates the transcoding needed today when using a model
in a different tool or for a different purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDL is also designed to be clear and explicit about model features, concentrating
on WHAT the model is saying rather than mechanics of HOW values are calculated.
This should mean that MDL is easier to share across disciplines, for example
between pharmacologists and statisticians or vice versa. Neither discipline should
have to learn tools used by the other in order to share models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;will-the-new-language-mdl-really-be-better-than-existing-languages&#34;&gt;Will the new language (MDL) really be better than existing languages?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MDL is better than existing languages in the sense that it allows models to
be specified in the same language, regardless of the target tool to be used for
a given task (e.g. estimation), and regardless of whether the model is intended
to be used for estimation, simulation, or optimal design, or all of the above.
No existing language today allows this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-would-modellers-want-to-learn-a-new-language-mdl&#34;&gt;Why would modellers want to learn a new language (MDL)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experienced modellers, who apply several different tools in their work, would
want to learn MDL to get the benefit of not having to transcode models for use
in different tools or for different purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginners or less experienced modellers would want to learn MDL because this
will allow them to work with several different tools without having to learn
several different languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDL is an Open Source language - it will be possible for the user community to
contribute to MDL, to extend MDL, to evolve MDL. This is not possible with
proprietary languages. They key thing is that changes within MDL map to
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pharmml.org&#34;&gt;PharmML&lt;/a&gt; features, in order to facilitate down-stream
conversion to target software like NONMEM, Monolix, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;but-i-only-use-nonmem&#34;&gt;But I only use NONMEM&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might only use NONMEM for estimation, but you might want to use other tools
for simulation, like PKPDsim, RxODE, mlxR, mrgsolve&amp;hellip; At that point you will
need to recode the model from NMTRAN to C++, or R ODE representation using
the deSolve package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might also be interested in the open source tools for estimation, like
saemix, nlmixr, Stan etc. These tools do not have the same level of use as
NONMEM, but they represent a useful set of tools that are freely available for
nonlinear mixed effect modelling. These might be useful to illustrate your models
to anyone in the world, without assuming that they have licenses for proprietary
tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-i-get-started-with-mdl&#34;&gt;How can I get started with MDL?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;are-there-any-examples-and-descriptions-of-the-new-ddmore-languages-available&#34;&gt;Are there any examples and descriptions of the new DDMoRe languages available?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When installing the Interoperability Framework, it comes with a UseCases project
folder pre-installed in the workspace. Within this folder are examples of models
in MDL and associated R scripts showing how to use these models for typical
modelling tasks. These models are also available via &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/p/ddmore/use.cases/ci/master/tree/MDL/Product5.1/&#34;&gt;SourceForge git repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-tools-are-available-for-writing-mdl&#34;&gt;What tools are available for writing MDL?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/&#34;&gt;MDL-Editor&lt;/a&gt;
is available for download. This is a cross-platform, Eclipse-based Integrated
Development Environment (IDE) for writing MDL models incorporating syntax
highlighting and grammar checks. It is available for Windows (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86.zip&#34;&gt;32bit&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;64bit&lt;/a&gt;),
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-linux.gtk.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-macosx.cocoa.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Mac OS&lt;/a&gt;. Simply download the zip file and unzip to an appropriate location.
An update site has been configured within Eclipse so that future updates to the
MDL-Editor can be retrieved from within Eclipse without having to download
another zip file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MDL Editor can be used to develop models using MDL and to export these models
to PharmML, ready for upload to the DDMoRe repository: &lt;a href=&#34;http://repository.ddmore.eu&#34;&gt;http://repository.ddmore.eu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;but-what-if-i-want-to-run-the-models&#34;&gt;But what if I want to run the models?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ddmore.eu/instructions/user-guides&#34;&gt;ddmore.eu&lt;/a&gt;
website you&amp;rsquo;ll also find instructions for downloading and installing the DDMoRe
Interoperability Framework Standalone Execution Environment (SEE) demonstrator.
The SEE installers are available from &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/projects/ddmore/files/install/SEE/Demonstrator-2.0.0/&#34;&gt;Sourceforge&lt;/a&gt;.
The SEE is a DDMoRe demonstration product which includes R, NONMEM, Monolix,
BUGS, PFIM, PopED, simulx (from the &lt;code&gt;mlxR&lt;/code&gt; R package). The SEE is only available
for Windows at present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-resources-are-there-to-help-me-learn-mdl-and-use-the-editor-see&#34;&gt;What resources are there to help me learn MDL and use the editor / SEE?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL_GGUkhbiP3t0Q7wTqkQdMAw7yuC8xWa-&#34;&gt;YouTube playlist&lt;/a&gt;
is available for videos detailing how to get started with the software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A set of Use Case examples is provided with the SEE, which are also available on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/p/ddmore/use.cases/ci/master/tree/MDL/Product5.1/&#34;&gt;SourceForge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;but-won-t-it-take-ages-for-me-to-learn-mdl&#34;&gt;But won&amp;rsquo;t it take ages for me to learn MDL&amp;hellip;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DDMoRe training courses devoted two days to learning about MDL, and language
basics. Following these two days, the majority of learners were able to encode
models and with support from the example Use Cases, documentation and the user
community were able to encode the majority of MDL models that you see in the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://repository.ddmore.eu&#34;&gt;DDMoRe repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;converting-existing-code&#34;&gt;Converting existing code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;can-i-translate-code-from-nonmem-other-software-into-mdl-without-coding-from&#34;&gt;Can I translate code from NONMEM/other software into MDL without coding from&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;scratch?
For NONMEM, a tool is available for translating NMTRAN code into MDL. The tool
is available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://nmtran-to-mdl.mango-solutions.com/&#34;&gt;http://nmtran-to-mdl.mango-solutions.com/&lt;/a&gt;. Please, read the help
documentation since some additional information, and certain NMTRAN structure is
required to obtain a valid MDL. Alternatively, you can use the tool to generate
a template that you can further modify within the Interoperability Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;contributing-and-extending-mdl-definition&#34;&gt;Contributing and extending MDL definition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-can-i-report-a-problem-with-mdl&#34;&gt;How can I report a problem with MDL?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issues, bugs, feature requests, suggestions can be logged via
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/website/issues&#34;&gt;Github Issues page&lt;/a&gt;.
Please label your item with &amp;ldquo;Website&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;MDL Language&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;MDL-Editor&amp;rdquo; and the type
of issue (&amp;ldquo;bug&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;enhancement&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;help wanted&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;invalid&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;question&amp;rdquo;) so that we can
direct it to the right place for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-can-i-contribute-to-mdl-development&#34;&gt;How can I contribute to MDL development?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDL is an open language, which depends on community involvement to help refine
it, extend it and to ensure that it is useful to the community in expressing
the models that you use. We&amp;rsquo;re very happy for you to help us contribute to the
MDL community, website, language. This can be through:&lt;br /&gt;
  * submitting bugs and issues, feature requests&lt;br /&gt;
  * by refining the MDL documentation; or by adding new example Use Cases to
illustrate features&lt;br /&gt;
  * suggesting grammar and syntax features and changes. The way to do this is to
contribute to the Github repositories.Github maintains a useful &lt;a href=&#34;https://guides.github.com/activities/hello-world/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Getting Started&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
guide if you need help on how to contribute to the repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MDL Editor now available</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/24/mdleditor_announcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 16:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/24/mdleditor_announcement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE

/BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/&#34;&gt;MDL-Editor&lt;/a&gt; is now available for download. This is a cross-platform, Eclipse-based Integrated Development Environment (IDE) for writing MDL models incorporating syntax highlighting and grammar checks. It is available for Windows ( &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86.zip&#34;&gt;32bit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;64bit&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-linux.gtk.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-macosx.cocoa.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Mac OS&lt;/a&gt;. Simply download the zip file and unzip to an appropriate location. An update site has been configured within Eclipse so that future updates to the MDL-Editor can be retrieved from within Eclipse without having to download another zip file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MDL Editor can be used to develop models using MDL and to export these models to PharmML, ready for upload to the DDMoRe repository: &lt;a href=&#34;http://repository.ddmore.eu&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://repository.ddmore.eu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planned future enhancements to the MDL Editor include incorporation of Git version control and integration of R. To run models using MDL, the Interoperability Framework Standalone Execution Environment (SEE) is available from &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/projects/ddmore/files/install/SEE/Demonstrator-2.0.0/&#34;&gt;Sourceforge&lt;/a&gt;. This is a demonstration product which includes R, NONMEM, Monolix, BUGS, PFIM, PopED, simulx (from the &lt;code&gt;mlxR&lt;/code&gt; R package). The SEE is only available for Windows at present. Installation instructions and associated documentation is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://ddmore.eu/instructions/user-guides&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A zip file of examples (UseCases) and the MDL User Guide and Reference Manual will also be available for download at the same site. These examples should assist the user in writing models from scratch as they illustrate many of the more commonly used model features encoded with MDL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can submit bugs, issues, feature requests and comments on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/mdl-ide/issues&#34;&gt;MDL-IDE Github Issues&lt;/a&gt; tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source-code for the MDL Editor is available: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/mdl-ide&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/mdl-ide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and source-code for the MDL Eclipse plugin is also available separately: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/mdleditorplugin&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/mdleditorplugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD




/BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About MDL</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 10:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/page/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;welcome-to-the-ddmore-model-description-language-mdl-community-page&#34;&gt;Welcome to the DDMoRe Model Description Language (MDL) Community page.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website will provide a resource for anyone wishing to encode models with MDL,
will help you understand MDL structure and features and provides a place for you
to log bugs, issues, feature requests and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-mdl&#34;&gt;What is MDL?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MDL is a human writeable and human readable language designed to describe
pharmacometric models. It is intended to be largely agnostic about the choice of
target tool. MDL should facilitate clear and unambiguous definition of models,
with information conveyed in a consistent manner to the PharmML representation
and onwards to the target software specific code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-can-i-find-details-about-writing-models-using-mdl-language-and-grammar&#34;&gt;Where can I find details about writing models using MDL language and grammar?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ddmore.eu/sites/ddmore/files/instructions/pdf/MDLUserGuide_1.1_PublicRelease_August2016_0.pdf&#34;&gt;MDL User Guide and Reference Manual&lt;/a&gt;
is available online in PDF format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-tools-are-available-for-writing-and-editing-mdl&#34;&gt;What tools are available for writing and editing MDL?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/&#34;&gt;MDL-Editor&lt;/a&gt;
is available for download. This is a cross-platform, Eclipse-based Integrated
Development Environment (IDE) for writing MDL models incorporating syntax
highlighting and grammar checks. It is available for Windows (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86.zip&#34;&gt;32bit&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;64bit&lt;/a&gt;),
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-linux.gtk.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-macosx.cocoa.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Mac OS&lt;/a&gt;. Simply download the zip file and unzip to an appropriate location.
An update site has been configured within Eclipse so that future updates to the
MDL-Editor can be retrieved from within Eclipse without having to download
another zip file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MDL Editor can be used to develop models using MDL and to export these models
to PharmML, ready for upload to the DDMoRe repository: &lt;a href=&#34;http://repository.ddmore.eu&#34;&gt;http://repository.ddmore.eu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;but-what-if-i-want-to-run-the-models&#34;&gt;But what if I want to run the models?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ddmore.eu/instructions/user-guides&#34;&gt;ddmore.eu&lt;/a&gt;
website you&amp;rsquo;ll also find instructions for downloading and installing the DDMoRe
Interoperability Framework Standalone Execution Environment (SEE) demonstrator.
The SEE installers are available from &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/projects/ddmore/files/install/SEE/Demonstrator-2.0.0/&#34;&gt;Sourceforge&lt;/a&gt;.
The SEE is a DDMoRe demonstration product which includes R, NONMEM, Monolix,
BUGS, PFIM, PopED, simulx (from the &lt;code&gt;mlxR&lt;/code&gt; R package). The SEE is only available
for Windows at present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-resources-are-there-to-help-me-learn-mdl-and-use-the-editor-see&#34;&gt;What resources are there to help me learn MDL and use the editor / SEE?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL_GGUkhbiP3t0Q7wTqkQdMAw7yuC8xWa-&#34;&gt;YouTube playlist&lt;/a&gt;
is available for videos detailing how to get started with the software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A set of Use Case examples is provided with the SEE, which are also available on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/p/ddmore/use.cases/ci/master/tree/MDL/Product5.1/&#34;&gt;SourceForge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-coming-on-this-website&#34;&gt;What is coming on this website?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the near future we hope to provide:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An online wiki format of the MDL User Guide and Reference Manual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answers to Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An issues log for capturing bugs, feature requests and suggestions for MDL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A walkthrough of the MDL Use Case examples explaining and annotating the code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;authors-and-contributors&#34;&gt;Authors and Contributors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike K Smith &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MikeKSmith&#34;&gt;@MikeKSmith&lt;/a&gt; is the lead user for MDL.
Stuart Moodie &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stumoodie&#34;&gt;@stumoodie&lt;/a&gt; is the technical lead for MDL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;support-or-contact&#34;&gt;Support or Contact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issues, bugs, feature requests, suggestions can be logged via
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/website/issues&#34;&gt;Github Issues page&lt;/a&gt;.
Please label your item with &amp;ldquo;Website&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;MDL Language&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;MDL-Editor&amp;rdquo; and the type
of issue (&amp;ldquo;bug&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;enhancement&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;help wanted&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;invalid&amp;rdquo;,&amp;ldquo;question&amp;rdquo;) so that we can
direct it to the right place for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email contact information will be added very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research leading to these results has received support from the Innovative Medicines Initiative Joint Undertaking under grant agreement n° 115156, resources of which are composed of financial contribution from the European Union&amp;rsquo;s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) and EFPIA companies’ in kind contribution. The DDMoRe project is also financially supported by contributions from Academic and SME partners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About MDL and this website</title>
      <link>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/22/about_mdl_and_this_website/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 10:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.mdl.community/2016/11/22/about_mdl_and_this_website/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE

/BLOGDOWN-BODY-BEFORE --&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;welcome-to-the-ddmore-model-description-language-mdl-community-page.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Welcome to the DDMoRe Model Description Language (MDL) Community page.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website will provide a resource for anyone wishing to encode models with MDL, will help you understand MDL structure and features and provides a place for you to log bugs, issues, feature requests and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-mdl&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is MDL?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MDL is a human writeable and human readable language designed to describe pharmacometric models. It is intended to be largely agnostic about the choice of target tool. MDL should facilitate clear and unambiguous definition of models, with information conveyed in a consistent manner to the PharmML representation and onwards to the target software specific code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;where-can-i-find-out-more-about-mdl&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where can I find out more about MDL?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ddmore.eu/sites/ddmore/files/instructions/pdf/MDLUserGuide_1.1_PublicRelease_August2016_0.pdf&#34;&gt;MDL User Guide and Reference Manual&lt;/a&gt; is available online in PDF format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ddmore.eu/instructions/user-guides&#34;&gt;ddmore.eu&lt;/a&gt; website you’ll also find instructions for downloading and installing the DDMoRe Interoperability Framework Standalone Execution Environment (SEE) demonstrator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/&#34;&gt;MDL-Editor&lt;/a&gt; is available for download. This is a cross-platform, Eclipse-based Integrated Development Environment (IDE) for writing MDL models incorporating syntax highlighting and grammar checks. It is available for Windows ( &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86.zip&#34;&gt;32bit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-win32.win32.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;64bit&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-linux.gtk.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.mdl.community/repository/mdl-ide/products/1.6.0/eu.ddmore.mdleditor.site-1.6.0-SNAPSHOT-macosx.cocoa.x86_64.zip&#34;&gt;Mac OS&lt;/a&gt;. Simply download the zip file and unzip to an appropriate location. An update site has been configured within Eclipse so that future updates to the MDL-Editor can be retrieved from within Eclipse without having to download another zip file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MDL Editor can be used to develop models using MDL and to export these models to PharmML, ready for upload to the DDMoRe repository: &lt;a href=&#34;http://repository.ddmore.eu&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://repository.ddmore.eu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL_GGUkhbiP3t0Q7wTqkQdMAw7yuC8xWa-&#34;&gt;YouTube playlist&lt;/a&gt; is available for videos detailing how to get started with the software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A set of Use Case examples is provided with the SEE, which are also available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/p/ddmore/use.cases/ci/master/tree/MDL/Product5.1/&#34;&gt;SourceForge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-coming-on-this-website&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is coming on this website?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the near future we hope to provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An online wiki format of the MDL User Guide and Reference Manual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answers to Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An issues log for capturing bugs, feature requests and suggestions for MDL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A walkthrough of the MDL Use Case examples explaining and annotating the code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;authors-and-contributors&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Authors and Contributors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike K Smith &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;[@MikeKSmith]&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MikeKSmith&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/MikeKSmith&lt;/a&gt;) is the lead user for MDL. Stuart Moodie &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;[@stumoodie]&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stumoodie&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/stumoodie&lt;/a&gt;) is the technical lead for MDL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;support-or-contact&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Support or Contact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Issues, bugs, feature requests, suggestions can be logged via the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ModelDefinitionLanguage/website/issues&#34;&gt;Github Issues page&lt;/a&gt;. Please label your item with “Website”, “MDL Language”, or “MDL-Editor” and the type of issue (“bug”,“enhancement”,“help wanted”,“invalid”,“question”) so that we can direct it to the right place for action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email contact information will be added very soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research leading to these results has received support from the Innovative Medicines Initiative Joint Undertaking under grant agreement n° 115156, resources of which are composed of financial contribution from the European Union’s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) and EFPIA companies’ in kind contribution. The DDMoRe project is also financially supported by contributions from Academic and SME partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;!-- BLOGDOWN-HEAD




/BLOGDOWN-HEAD --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
